Finding Aid for Helen W. Berthelot papers, 1948-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helen W. Berthelot papers 1948-1996
Berthelot, Helen W.
35.2 linear feet
85748 Aa 2
Campaign manager for G. Mennen Williams and official of the Communications Workers of America. Correspondence, schedules and publications concerning politics, election campaigns, 1954-1976, labor, communications satellites, the Democratic Party, and the Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Helen W. Berthelot (Donor no. 4485 ) in several accessions.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Helen W. Berthelot was a pioneer in the labor movement and in Michigan state politics. As an official for the Communications Workers of America, she was the first full-time woman labor lobbyist in Washington, and the first woman to run a statewide political campaign in Michigan.
In the 1920s, Berthelot moved to Michigan from Massachusetts, where she married and had two children. She began work as a telephone operator for Michigan Bell, and found herself the sole provider for her family after her husband died. During the unionization of Michigan Bell in the mid-1940s, Berthelot was elected to several positions within the Communication Workers of America (CWA), eventually becoming a lobbyist in Washington for CWA, a position she held from 1953 to 1969.
Berthelot began her political work as a volunteer in G. Mennen William's gubernatorial campaign in 1948. She soon gained the reputation as a quiet force behind the Democratic party, and became Governor William's campaign manager for the 1954, 1956, and 1958 campaigns. In 1960, Berthelot was the state coordinator for Democratic campaigns. She managed Neil Staebler's successful election as congressman-at-large in 1962, and, in 1964, his campaign for governor. Berthelot managed William's fall campaign for the U. S. Senate in 1966. During the late 1960s and early 1970s, she was active in the campaigns of several presidential hopefuls, including Hubert Humphrey's 1968 presidential bid. In 1972, Berthelot accepted the job of office manager for the Democratic National Convention in Miami Beach.
During the 1980s, Berthelot stepped back from the political scene and began research on the rise of the Democratic party in Michigan during the 1940s, culminating in the book Win Some, Lose Some: G. Mennen Williams and the New Democrats, which was published in 1995. She passed away on May 6, 1996 at the age of 92.
The papers of Helen Berthelot have been arranged into seven series by date and topic. The files arranged primarily by date are largely unprocessed and relate to her activities in the Michigan Democratic Party and as a lobbyist for the Communications Workers of America. The strengths of the collection is the material relating to the various campaigns of G. Mennen Williams for governor, 1948 to 1958, the Presidential campaigns of 1960 and 1964, and Williams's campaign for the United States Senate in 1966. The collection also includes correspondence, photographs, and material related to the publication and reception of Win Some, Lose Some: G. Mennen Williams and the New Democrats.
Subjects:
Communications Workers of America.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--United States--1954.; Elections--United States--1956.; Elections--United States--1958.; Elections--United States--1960.; Elections--United States--1962.; Elections--United States--1964.; Elections--United States--1966.; Elections--United States--1968.; Elections--United States--1972.; Elections--United States--1976.; Telecommunication--Employees--Labor unions.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Satellites.; United States. Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Women in politics--Michigan.; Berthelot, Helen W.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Berthelot, Helen W.; Democratic Nation Convention (1960: Los Angeles); Democratic Party (Mich.); Express highways--Michigan.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Michigan. State Fair Commission.; Politicians--Michigan.; Politics and government--Michigan.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Democratic Party / Communication Workers of America
  The Democratic Party/Communication Workers of America series documents Berthelot's involvement in the Democratic Party, especially her role as campaign manager for G. Mennen Williams. It also contains material related to Berthelot's involvement in the Communication Workers of America.
  - 1942-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - 1956 (Box 3)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - 1958 (Box 5)
  - 1958 (Box 6)
  - 1958 (Box 32)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 8)
  - 1960 (Box 9)
  - 1960 (Box 10)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 11)
  - 1962 (Box 12)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 13)
  - 1964 (Box 14)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 15)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 16)
  - 1966 (Box 17)
  - 1966 (Box 18)
  - 1966 (Box 19)
  - 1966 (Box 20)
  - 1966 (Box 21)
  - 1966 (Box 33)
    (also includes clippings about Helen W. Berthelot and miscellaneous)
  - 1967 (Box 22)
  - 1968 (Box 23)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 24)
  - 1969-1972 (Box 25)
  - 1973-1978 (Box 26)
    (also includes miscellaneous Communications Workers of America Publications)
- Topical
  The Topical series contains material related to Berthelot's involvement in the Communication Workers of America.
  - Communications Workers of America (Box 27)
  - Convention Proceedings and Executive Board Reports (Box 27)
  - Communications Satellites 1961-1965 (Box 28)
  - Communications Satellites 1961-1965 (Box 29)
  - Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services 1966-1970 (Box 30)
  - Democratic Advisory Committee on Political Organization 1952-1960 (Box 31)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters both to and from Berthelot. The correspondence is covers a wide-range of political, personal, and professional topics from 1948-1996.
  - 1948-1996 undated, 27 folders (Box 34)
- Newsclippings 1951-1995
  The Newsclippings series (1951-1995) consists of two folders of newspaper clippings related to Michigan Politics and the Michigan State Fair. There is also a folder of political cartoons.
  - Michigan Politics 1951-1966, 1986-1988, 1993-1995 (Box 34)
  - Michigan State Fair 1950, 1952, 1958 (Box 34)
  - Political Cartoons 1957-1958, 1964-1968 (Box 34)
- Political Activities 1948-1996
  The Political Activities series (1948-1996) includes additional material related to Berthelot's career in the Michigan Democratic Party. Materials include notes, flyers, memorandums, and publications related to state and national campaigns and political figures.
  - Berthelot Biographical Material 1950-1966, 1990-1996 (Box 34)
  - Contents of Scrapbook 1950s-1970s (Box 34)
    (includes photographs and letters of Lyndon B. Johnson, John F. Kennedy, Hubert Humphrey, and other Democratic Party leaders)
  - Michigan
    - General 1949-1960 (Box 34)
    - General 1961-1983 (Box 34)
    - Berthelot's State Legislature Campaign 1948 (Box 34)
    - Hart, Philip 1958, 1967, 1969, 1976 (Box 34)
    - State Fair Board 1954, 1958-1959, 1961 (Box 34)
    - Williams, G. Mennen
      - General (including tributes and obituaries) 1964-1990 (Box 34)
      - Gubernatorial Campaigns 1948-1960 (Box 34)
      - Mackinac Bridge Dedication 1958 (Box 34)
      - U.S. Senate Campaign 1966 (Box 34)
  - National
    - General 1960-1979 (Box 34)
    - Humphrey, Hubert Presidential Campaign 1968 (Box 34)
    - Kennedy, John F. (Presidential Campaign and Inauguration) 1960-1961 (Box 34)
- Photographs, circa 1940s-1990s
  The Photographs series (ca. 1940s-1990s) contains personal and professional photographs of Berthelot, the Michigan State Fair, the Mackinac Bridge Dedication, G. Mennen Williams, Philip Hart, and various other Michigan and national Democratic political figures.
  - Berthelot, Helen
    - Personal Snapshots circa 1950s-1990s (Box 34)
    - Reception for Berthelot and her book 1995 (Box 34)
  - Mackinac Bridge Dedication 1958 (Box 34)
  - Michigan State Fair
    - Undated, 1950-1956 (Box 34)
    - 1957 (Box 34)
    - 1959, 1961-1962, 1966 (Box 34)
  - Political Figures
    - Michigan
      - General circa 1950s-1980s (Box 34)
      - Democratic Women's Groups 1960, 1962 (Box 34)
      - Hart, Philip circa 1950s-1960s (Box 34)
    - National circa 1950s-1975 (Box 34)
    - Portraits (Berthelot, political figures) circa 1940s-1990s (Box 34)
    - Williams, G. Mennen
      - circa 1949-1959 (Box 34)
      - circa 1960s, 1986-1987 (Box 34)
    - Williams Family Portraits 1948, 1960, 1966 (Box 34)
  - Michigan (Box 36)
    (includes photographs of Mackinac Bridge and aerial photographs of Detroit and of highway interchanges)
  - Politics (Box 36)
    (includes photographs of Williams with Harry Truman and John F. Kennedy, a photograph of Berthelot with Estes Kefauver, the 1960 Democratic National Convention, and a political cartoon by Frank Williams)
- Writing, Research, and Publicity Materials (Win Some, Lose Some)
  The Writing, Research, and Publicity Materials series documents the writing and publication of Berthelot's book Win Some, Lose Some: G. Mennen Williams and the New Democrats. The materials in this series include a manuscript of the book with pre-publication corrections, drafts, notes, research materials, book reviews, correspondence, and publicity materials.
  - Appendix Materials undated (Box 35)
    (includes photocopied material from 1954 and 1986)
  - Book Reviews and Reception (Win Some, Lose Some), 1995 (Box 35)
  - Book Revision 1991 (Box 35)
    (includes correspondence, manuscript reviews, and handwritten notes)
  - Collected Materials Used for Win Some, Lose Some, 1955-1988 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Corrections and Suggestions 1987-1988, undated (Box 35)
  - Correspondence 1988-1995 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence with Wayne State University Press 1991-1995 (Box 35)
  - Development of Front Matter and Blurbs 1991-1992, undated (Box 35)
    (includes photocopied material from 1960)
  - Material from Interviews with Helen W. Berthelot 1991, undated (Box 35)
  - Material from Interviews with Others 1992, undated (Box 35)
  - Notes and Drafts undated, 3 folders (Box 35)
  - Original Manuscript with Corrections 1994, 6 folders (Box 35)
  - Permissions 1988-1995 (Box 35)
  - Photographs and Illustrations, Originals, 1948, 1959, 1986, undated (Box 35)
  - Political and Campaign Advice undated (Box 35)
  - Promotional Materials 1994, undated (Box 35)
  - Research Materials for Rewrite 1992-1993, undated (Box 35)